Okay בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody, happy מוצאי חנוכה, Motzei Chanukah, אסרו
חג. Isru Chag. Today’s דף Daf is דף כג Daf Chaf Gimmel
23. We pick up with the משנה Mishna on the bottom of
כב עמוד ב Chaf Bet Amud Bet and we are moving to
the opening משנה Mishna dealt with the two that are four, some
degree of discussion of a קרבן, Korban, to some degree a discussion
in the but then we got to a question about how much
you have to eat to transgress, given an opportunity for the גמרא
Gemara to discuss a lot of things. What are the transgressions? Is
it שבועת שוא, Shvuat Shav, שבועת שקר, Shvuat Sheker, לא יחל דברו?
Lo Yechel Devaro?
You know, how then we got into a lot of questions about
התפסת שבועה, Hatfasat Shvua, a lot of discussions recently about the issue
about קונם Konam and about when you say אכילה Achila and different
ways in which you can say אכילה, Achila, different types of אכילה,
Achila, whether they refer would refer to a כלשהו Kolshehu or a
smallest amount or כזית. Kezayit. We’ve also seen the principle of מושבע
ועומד. Mushba Ve’omed. So we’ve seen like, covered a lot of different
principles.
And now we move to the משנה Mishna and the משנה Mishna
is going to get us into something that yesterday the גמרא Gemara
sort of drew on, which was the idea about how you frame
your שבועה Shvua and then if if you transgress it, could determine
multiple קרבנות, Korbanot, do we look at it as multiple שבועות Shvuot
or just as one שבועה Shvua and one קרבן? Korban? So let’s
take a look at the משנה. Mishna. שבועה שלא אוכל. Shvua Shelo
Ochal. Somebody takes an oath not to eat. ואכל ושתה Ve’achal Veshashata
and he ate and he drank. So even though those are two
separate acts, but his שבועה Shvua was only one act. So halakhically
and implicit in this משנה Mishna which is going to be the
focus of the גמרא, Gemara, we see drinking included in the term
eating. Eating would mean consuming, it would include drinking. So therefore, yes,
both of those were transgressions, but since they all
fall under the rubric of אכילה, Achila, so it’s two of the
same עבירות. Aveiras. And two of the same עבירות, Aveiras, אינו חייב
אלא אחת, Eino Chayav Ela Achat, you only bring one קרבן. Korban.
Again, this is assuming that you don’t become aware in the middle.
So it’s like eating two כזיתים Kezaysim of חמץ Chametz on פסח,
Pesach, two כזיתים Kezaysim of forbidden fat, right? If you don’t become
aware in the middle that you’ve sinned and are obligated in a
קרבן, Korban, even though you’ve transgressed twice, since it’s all the same
sin, it’s one קרבן. Korban. Okay,
now. שבועה שלא אוכל ושלא אשתה. Shvua Shelo Ochal Veshelo Eshte. Let’s
say you say, a guy says an oath I won’t eat and
I won’t drink. Now again, what’s important is he identifies two acts,
but also even though he doesn’t say today שבועה שלא אוכל Shvua
Shelo Ochal and then a day later or a minute later or
second later שבועה שלא אשתה, Shvua Shelo Eshte, he doesn’t use the
word שבועה Shvua for each one. So I might have thought that
even though he’s naming two acts, we conceptualize that as one שבועה.
Shvua. The חידוש Chiddush of the משנה Mishna and we saw this
yesterday is that it is conceptualized as two distinct שבועות. Shvuot. Okay,
because he mentioned these two acts. So therefore ואכל ושתה, Ve’achal Veshashata,
he eats and he drinks. Even if he does not become aware
in the middle that he’s sinned, חייב שתים. Chayav Shtayim. He’s חייב
Chayav for two קרבנות Korbanot because those are two distinct acts. It’s
like today he said a שבועה Shvua I won’t eat and tomorrow
he said a שבועה Shvua I won’t drink. So they’re completely separate
שבועות Shvuot and then he and then he transgresses, excuse me, not
just two acts, two separate sins. Okay, so and therefore because they’re
two שבועות, Shvuot, they’re categorized as two separate sins and therefore two
קרבנות. Korbanot. Now again, you might say one minute, I get that
they’re separate שבועות, Shvuot, but it’s the same transgression. You’re transgressing the
prohibition right about taking God’s name in vain or שבועת שוא Shvuat
Shav or שבועת שקר, Shvuat Sheker, not God’s name in vain, whatever.
Okay, so isn’t it still the same עבירה Aveira even if it
comes through two separate שבועות? Shvuot? So I think the best,
you know, intuitively had I not seen this משנה Mishna I would
have said definitely it’s all the same עבירה, Aveira, one קרבן, Korban,
right? Who cares, you know, if the type of שבועה Shvua that
you’re transgressing is different.
But that’s not clearly one of the things this משנה Mishna is
teaching is that it is seen as two distinct עבירות. Aveiras.
And the best analogy is שבת, Shabbos, right? By שבת Shabbos if
I cook, I forgot it was שבת, Shabbos, so I cook or
let’s say forget, let’s make it an easier case. I both forgot
it was forbidden to cook on שבת Shabbos and I forgot it
was forbidden to make a fire. And I make a fire and
I cook and I don’t realize either of those in the middle.
So then I bring two sin offerings. Okay, because those are two
distinct מלאכות. Melachos. Fine, they’re two distinct מלאכות Melachos but I only
transgressed one sin. The sin is don’t do מלאכה Melacha on שבת,
Shabbos, don’t violate שבת, Shabbos, I transgressed it twice. But no, because
the תורה Torah tells you this idea of מלאכות, Melachos,
חילוק מלאכות, Chiluk Melachos, that means we look at each one as
a separate sin even though it’s all just a variation of violating
שבת. Shabbos. And therefore two sin offerings. So that is part of
the חידוש Chiddush here by a שבועה Shvua as well. At the
end of the day, and by the way, שבועה Shvua is very
unusual. There’s no כרת Kareth you
know, so it’s not one of those weighty ones from the perspective
of כרת. Kareth. Also it’s not a standard sin offering, it’s an
עולה ויורד. Oleh Ve’yored. But part of the חידוש Chiddush of this
משנה, Mishna, there’s two big חידושים Chiddushim which is number one is
if I make two separate שבועות Shvuot I bring two קרבנות Korbanot
even though I’ve only really transgressed the same עבירה Aveira twice but
because they’re two separate שבועות Shvuot they’re considered two separate sins and
therefore two קרבנות. Korbanot. And number two even if I don’t use
the word שבועה Shvua for each one, even if I just bundle
it up, it sounds like it’s one
שבועה. Shvua. שבועה shavua he won’t eat and drink, we call that
two שבועות shavuoses and therefore two קרבנות. korbanot. Okay, so that’s the
open basic חידוש chiddush of this משנה, mishna, you know, before we
even get to more complex cases, there’s a lot of חידושים chiddushim
there.
Okay, now, שבועה שלא אוכל, shavua shelo ochel, a guy takes a
שבועה shavua he won’t eat, ואכל פת חיטין ופת שעורין ופת כוסמין,
v’achal pas chittin u’pas seorin u’pas kusmin, he eats three different types
of bread, normal one and barley and bran, or whatever כוסמין kusmin
is, spelt. ואכל v’achal okay, וכוסמין. v’kusmin. אינו
חייב אלא אחת, eino chayav ella achas, so those are all just
three ways of transgressing the same שבועה, shavua, so he only brings
one sin offering if he does it unawares. שבועה שלא אוכל פת
חיטין ופת שעורין ופת כוסמין, shavua shelo ochel pas chittin u’pas seorin
u’pas kusmin, if somebody says I swear I won’t eat wheat bread
and barley bread and spelt bread, so those are halachically defined as
these three separate שבועות. shavuoses. אינו חייב אלא אחת eino chayav ella
achas I’m sorry, did I... I’m looking at... ואכל v’achal and he
eats all three of them, חייב על כל אחת ואחת. chayav al
kol achas v’achas. So those are three separate שבועות, shavuoses, three separate
sins, and therefore three קרבנות. korbanot. שבועה שלא אשתה ושתה משקין הרבה,
shavua shelo eshte v’shata mashkin harbe,
so he says a שבועה shavua he won’t drink and he drinks
many different types of liquids, אינו חייב אלא
אחת, eino chayav ella achas, again, multiple transgressions of the multiple violations
of the same transgression, one קרבן. korban. שבועה שלא אשתה יין ושמן
ודבש, shavua shelo eshte yayin v’shemen u’dvash, guy says a שבועה shavua
I won’t drink wine and oil and honey. ושתה, v’shata, so that
is defined as three separate שבועות, shavuoses, even though there would be
no other way to bundle those together, but the fact that that’s
what he said is defined as three separate שבועות. shavuoses. ושתה, v’shata,
and he drinks all three of them, חייב על כל אחת ואחת.
chayav al kol achas v’achas. That’s not different than the first
part.
Correct, it’s just I don’t know.
Okay, we’ll see a little bit in the גמרא.
gemara. Eating honey though, I mean, like, hasn’t it nothing to do...
That’s an oh wait, it’s an interesting question that things like honey
and oil are defined as drinking even though, yes, you can pour
it in your mouth, but we would more call that an eating
of them. And also oil, do you drink oil? Actually, I knew
somebody who had a diet and the diet required him to drink
like a cup of oil a day. And that was supposed to
like get all the make him not want to eat or get
all the other food to just slide out of his body. So
I guess it’s theoret- but you know, you might say that’s like
שתיה כלאחר יד. shtiya k’lo’achar yad.
I agree, surely about honey.
I think it’s a good question. So maybe that’s part of the
answer to what the חידוש chiddush here is. The חידוש chiddush is
that since it’s a liquid, it’s included in the איסור issur of
שתיה shtiya even though it’s not a normal thing that’s like what
you know it’s not a normal thing that we would drink. But
you’re right, that is a חידוש chiddush here. Okay, anyway, so that’s
considered not three transgressions of the same sin but three separate sins
and therefore three קרבנות. korbanot. Now, שבועה שלא אוכל, shavua shelo ochel,
if he takes an oath not to eat, ואכל אוכלים שאינם ראויים
לאכילה, v’achal ochalim she’einam reuyim l’achila, and he drinks things that are
not fit to be eaten, you know, disgusting things, dirt, or whatever
they are, ושתה משקין שאינם ראויים לשתיה, v’shata mashkin she’einam reuyim l’shtiya,
or liquids that are not fit to be drunk, which actually is
interesting given our discussion before, but I guess here not fit to
be doesn’t mean that like it would be like, you know, disgusting
to consume them. I mean it’s not disgusting to consume honey. I
guess the oil is an interesting question from that perspective. Anyway, פטור,
patur, you are exempt because that’s not included in the word eat
and drink. We would apply normal halachic definitions to that, which also
gets to the question about the amount. You need a כזית, kezayit,
which is what was debated before. But in terms of the things
that are referred to, the same way we normally say that halachically
you only transgress sins if you eat something and if it’s fit
to be eaten, here too it’s the same, like by פסח pesach
or יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, then you wouldn’t be עובר. over. Yeah.
שבועה שלא אוכל ואכל נבילות וטריפות שקצים ורמשים, shavua shelo ochel v’achal
neveilos u’treifos shekatzim u’remasim, however, if a guy takes an oath not
to eat and he eats non-kosher food, in that case, like, you
know, pork and dead carcasses, in that case חייב, chayav, you are
transgressed because it’s even it is fit to be eaten from a
physical perspective. It’s prohibited to be eaten, but it is fit to
be eaten. רבי שמעון פוטר, Rabbi Shimon poter, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
exempts. Now, presumably, he exempts, does he exempt because he doesn’t consider
that fit to be eaten, or does he exempt because of the
reason the גמרא gemara says, מושבע ועומד? mushba v’omed? They’re already prohibited
to eat it, so a שבועה shavua doesn’t fall on something that
you’re already, you know, bound by a שבועה shavua not to do.
Does it mean twice the time? Right, exactly. So, אמר, amar, now,
a person says, קונם אשתי נהנית לי אם אכלתי היום. konam ishti
nehenis li im achalti hayom. So this is interesting. One way of
making stuff forbidden for you is if somebody says like, you told
me you’re going to fast today and I don’t believe you, I
think I saw you sneak around, sneak and have a breakfast in
the other room. And a guy wants to say, no, I didn’t
eat anything. So he could do it by saying I take a
שבועה shavua that I didn’t eat anything today. But sometimes, maybe because
of the weight of taking a false שבועה shavua or I don’t
know exactly the full psychological, religious reasons, people would back up their
statements not by taking a שבועה shavua but by making a נדר.
neder. Now remember, a נדר neder just makes an object forbidden. How
do you back up your statement by making a נדר? neder? Because
you make it you make it conditional. You say if I ate
anything today, you could say like let all, you know, my food
in my house be forbidden to me. Here he says let my
wife be forbidden to me, okay? And therefore means we won’t be
able to have sex and so on. All right, so but that
is a way of making the consequence of my lie something that
will make things forbidden to me. So it’s actually more about נדרים,
nedarim, but it’s anyway, it’s here. So if a person says a
קונם, konam, again, we’ve learned that word קונם... konam... is like making
something like הקדש hekdesh a forbidden status, that my wife can't get
benefit, it's also an interesting phrase, נהני לי, nehani li, does that
mean I won't get benefit from her, she can't get benefit from
me? It sounds like I won't get benefit from her, but again
you have to learn נדרים, Nedarim, the phrasing is very distinctive. Okay.
My wife is forbidden in benefit to me אם אכלתי היום im
achalti hayom if I eat anything today והוא אכל נבלות וטרפות שקצים
ורמשים vehu achal neveilot utreifot shekatzim uremasim and he ate treif food,
so the הלכה halachah is הרי אשתו אסורה harei ishto asurah she
is forbidden, because as was implied before, this is considered an act
of eating. It's just there's a debate whether it's included in a
שבועה, shvuah, not because it's not eating, but because you're already forbidden
to eat it. But whether it's considered to eat to eat those
things, yes it is, and that's what the end of the משנה
mishnah makes clear. Okay, so now let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבי חייא בר אבין אמר שמואל Amar Rabbi Chiya
bar Avin Amar Shmuel שבועה שלא אוכל shvuah shelo ochel ושתה v'shatah
חייב. chayav. If somebody just says a שבועה shvuah that I won't
eat and he drinks, he would transgress. That's implicit in the משנה,
mishnah, we're just going to spell it out, that drinking is included
in the word אוכל. ochel. So שבועה shvuah I won't eat includes
also drinking. איבעית אימא סברא ואיבעית אימא קרא. Iba'it eima svara ve'iba'it
eima kra. If you want I can give you a logic for
it, if you want I can give you a verse. איבעית אימא
סברא Iba'it eima svara if I want I can just explain it
logically דאמר ליה אינש לחבריה d'amar lei inish lechaverei somebody will say
to his friend ניתו מידי neito midi let's go have something to
taste of something, let's go have a bite to eat ואזלו ואכלו
ושתו v'azlu v'achalu v'shatu and they go in and they eat and
they drink. Now, that's not much of a proof of anything, because
when you're drinking it still might be your drinking might just be
accompanying your eating, it doesn't mean you're referring to your drinking as
eating. So some גרסאות girsa'ot have they go in and they get
a drink. Okay, if somebody says, hey, let's go have something, let's
taste something, and they go and they get a drink and they
could go and get a drink. But you know what, I would
say two things: first of all, even if that's true, it's interesting
the גמרא Gemara shifted to the word let's go have something, let's
taste something, as opposed to let's go eat something. Maybe drinking is
included in tasting, who says it's included in the word eating? Right?
That's not a great proof. And number two, I don't know, as
far as I'm concerned, I've never heard anybody say let's go eat
something or taste something and all they do is drink. And if
it's a drinking that's including the eating, then it's then it's not
because the word eat referred to the drink. So anyway, the גמרא
Gemara is making a claim that in the vernacular, right, it is
sort of included.
Now תוספות Tosafot says, if you have the
גרסא girsa let's eat something and you go and eat and drink,
it is a proof, because if drinking wasn't included in eating, you
would have said let's go eat and drink, and then if you're
planning to drink as well. But again, that doesn't really prove it,
that just means that if while you're eating you're also drinking, that's
seen as sort of טפל, tafel, that's seen as like, you know,
as something secondary to the eating. It doesn't mean that drinking by
itself is included in that word. So the סברא svara is not
such a great סברא, svara, but anyway the גמרא's Gemara claim is
is that in the vernacular that is what it means. And that
gets somewhat back to the whole debate about רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
and the רבנן Rabanan about what's the minimum amount of size. How
much by your שבועה shvuah do we go by what those words
normally mean in הלכה, halachah, or how much do you know, what
some official definition of those words, or how much do we go
by what we think the guy was intending or what the vernacular
is? So the first explanation of the גמרא Gemara that drinking is
included is assuming that we would go by the vernacular. That's explanation
number one. Okay. ואיבעית אימא קרא Ve'iba'it eima kra and if you
want I'll give you a פסוק. pasuk. שתייה בכלל אכילה Shtiyah bichlal
achilah drinking is included in eating דאמר ריש לקיש d'amar Resh Lakish
because ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says, this is a classic discussion in
the גמרא Gemara that שתייה shtiyah in general in הלכה, halachah, not
just by a שבועה, shvuah, is included in the word to eat
דאמר ריש לקיש מנין לשתייה שהיא בכלל אכילה d'amar Resh Lakish minayin
lish'tiyah she'hi bichlal achilah where do I know that drinking is included
in eating שנאמר shene'emar because the verse says ואכלת לפני ה' אלהיך
במקום אשר יבחר לשכן שמו שם מעשר דגנך תירושך ויצהרך veachalta lifnei
Hashem Elokecha bamakom asher yivchar lshaken shemo sham ma’asar deganecha tiroshcha veyitzharecha
you shall eat before the Lord your God where He desires to
dwell His name there, this is about מעשר שני, ma’asar sheni, the
מעשר ma’asar of your of your grain and of your of your
what do you call it? Of your wine, thank you, ויצהרך, veyitzharecha,
it doesn't have the word ויצהרך, veyitzharecha, which is anyway your oil,
ותירושך v'tiroshcha
is wine, and it says ואכלת. veachalta. So also the word אכילה
achilah can also mean like to consume, right? It doesn't have to
mean to eat. And therefore, it includes liquids. וכתיב ואכלת Uchetiv veachalta
so that's a pretty good proof. So the גמרא Gemara says
I like the קרא kra better. What?
Yeah, the קרא kra is much better than the סברא. svara. ודילמא
Vedilma says the גמרא Gemara על ידי אניגרון. al yedei anigron.
How do you know that when it says eat wine, it means
drink wine? Maybe it means that you have some type of a
food, this food that was called אניגרון, anigron, or not even a
dip, some food that was made with wine in it. So I'm
going to have what's it like a a meat that was soaked
in wine, okay? So I'm eating my wine, because yes, there's ways
to eat your wine.
Okay. דאמר רבה בר שמואל אניגרון מיא דסלקא D'amar Rabbah bar Shmuel
anigron maya desilka אניגרון anigron is a type of a dish made
with beet water,
of course if it's beet water then it's a liquid, but anyway
made somehow with cooked
beets, ואנכיגרון מיא דכורפא. v'anchigron maya dechurpa.
But an אכסיגרון achsigron is something made with like just general cooked
vegetables. Anyway, the point being maybe eating wine here means eating, maybe
it means wine as part of some food dish.
Like a soup I'm thinking, right?
Maybe, yeah. Rashi says תבשיל של תרדין, tavshil shel tardin, right, like
a beet soup. Okay, or beet dish, a beet stew. אלא אמר
רב אחא בר יעקב מהכא, ela amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov me-hacha,
fine, the following verse. ונתתה הכסף בכל אשר תאוה נפשך, venatatah hakesef
be-chol asher t'aveh nafshecha, this is similar to the money of מעשר
שני, Ma'aser Sheni, use it with whatever your heart
desires. בבקר ובצאן וביין ובשכר, be-vakar u-va-tzon u-va-yayin u-va-shechar, and it says
wine and mead, or intoxicating liquid.
What's it do with eating though?
We're gonna get to it. יין חמרא הוא, yayin chamra hu, so
that's wine. וכתיב, u-chtiv, and then it says at the end of
the verse ואכלת, ve-achalta, and you should eat it לפני ה' אלהיך,
lifnei Hashem Elokecha, that's what it says at the end of the
verse. Okay, so you see again eating wine. ודילמא הכא נמי ע"י
אניגרון? v'dilma hacha nami al yedei anigron? So okay, same point, maybe
it means in some type of a food dish. No, שכר כתיב,
shechar ktiv, because it also says יין ושכר, yayin v'shechar, and שכר
shechar is a
ומידי דמשכר, u-midi d'meshaker, it's something that's actually intoxicating. So I guess
you could eat...
Does it have to be in that form or are we supposed
to be intoxicated?
Well, the assumption is that if you mix up a little wine
in something or a little beer in something or whatever, it's not
enough to have the potential of getting you drunk. You'd have to
have a gluttonous eating. So if it's something that can be getting
you drunk, it means you're drinking it straight. So the גמרא Gemara
says ומידי דמשכר, u-midi d'meshaker, something that has the potential of getting
you drunk. ודילמא דבילה קעילית? v'dilma dveilah k'ilit? Maybe that also refers
to not drinking beer or something like that. Maybe it refers to
eating these pressed figs,
these pressed figs from this place קעילית K'ilit that are supposed to
have the potential of getting you drunk. דתניא, d'tanya, it's shown in
the ברייתא, Baraisa, אכל דבילה קעילית ושתה דבש וחלב ונכנס למקדש ועבד,
achal dveilah k'ilit v'shata d'vash v'chalav v'nichnas l'mikdash v'avad, if you ate
those figs or you
drank honey or milk, those things have the ability to get you
drunk. Now I don't know if it's literally drunk, as opposed to
whatever, but maybe could be a little drowsy or confuse your thinking
or something. Anyway, ונכנס למקדש v'nichnas l'mikdash and you go into the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash ועבד v'avad and you do the service in
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, חייב, chayav, then you transgress for doing
service in a state of drunkenness.
Like on those winter mornings, I guess.
I guess. Anyway, אלא, ela, so anyway שכר shechar does could mean
something that you eat, it doesn't have to mean drinking beer and
therefore we don't have the idea that אכילה achilah means drink. אלא
גמר שכר שכר מנזיר. ela gamar shechar shechar mi-nazir. No, no, no.
We know שכר shechar here means really drinking something and intoxicating wine
and not just eating some food that can intoxicate. מה להלן יין,
ma le-halan yayin, the same way by נזיר Nazir we understand that
it says מיין ושכר יזיר חומץ יין mi-yayin v'shechar yazir chometz yayin
and there it's all about and there somehow we also know that
it's wine straight. אף כאן יין, af kan yayin, here too. Now
again, I don't know how we know there, we just learned the
other day that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says that you can dip
your bread into wine and eat it and be חייב. chayav. But
the word שכר shechar can't mean, the point is, the word שכר
shechar by a נזיר Nazir cannot mean like a fig or whatever
it is. We know that it's only in the world of wine
products and therefore for wine products to have the power to intoxicate
would have to be drinking wine straight. So here too we're talking
about drinking wine straight and it's included in the word אכילה. achilah.
So that's how we know that הלכתית halachically the word אכילה achilah
is seen to include also drinking. Now I want to say a
quick thing about the idea where the גמרא Gemara says if you
want I can give you a פסוק pasuk if you want I
can give you סברא. svara. This has been
brought
as a way of demonstrating, properly
so, about the power of תורה שבעל פה, Torah she-ba'al peh, the
power that the גמרא Gemara feels
like it's actually the exact opposite of I mean תורה שבעל פה's
Torah she-ba'al peh the opposite of fundamentalism and this statement encapsulates the
opposite of fundamentalism. 'Cause fundamentalism, we tend to describe fundamentalism as certain
extremism or whatever, but literally fundamentalism is basically sort of saying like
I'm just going by the simple meaning of the verse and I'm
not using my logic or whatever and I just completely submit to
the simple meaning of the verse. The idea that the גמרא Gemara
says look, if I want I could prove it to you from
סברא svara and if I want I could prove it from פסוק,
pasuk, means that my own human logic and reason is as strong
of an evidence to what the הלכה halacha would be as quoting
a verse. Now that doesn't prove to you what if in a
competition who wins if just saying that each one is sufficient. There's
actually other evidence that the גמרא Gemara says in a competition your
own סברא svara can win when the גמרא Gemara says something like
שביק לקרא דאיהו דחיק ומוקי אנפשיה shavik likra d'ihu dachik u-mokei anafsheh
which basically means forget the פסוק, pasuk, the פסוק's pasuk difficult, he's
going to explain it in a way that makes sense to him.
So the גמרא Gemara actually sometimes even indicates that your own סברא
svara beats out a פסוק. pasuk. But anyway here it certainly indicates
that it's of equivalent weight. And if you look at תוספות, Tosafot,
look at תוספות Tosafot אי בעית אימא קרא i-ba-it eima kra the
bottom little תוספות Tosafot on כב עמוד ב, kaf-bet amud-bet, תוספות Tosafot
says בסוף פרק קמא דקידושין גבי קושי בשכרות אמר הכי וכן בכמה
מקומות. be-sof perek kama d'Kiddushin gabi koshi be-shichrus amar hachi v'chen be-chama
mekomot. most. Number of places the גמרא Gemara uses this phrase. ותימא
כיון דאיכא סברא למה לי קרא? V'teima keivan d'ika svara lamma li
kra? תוספות Tosfos goes further, he says, what do you mean, if
you want I can quote you סברא svara if you want I
can quote you a פסוק. pasuk. Why are we bothering with a
פסוק? pasuk? We've got our סברא. svara. You know, he's either way
making the point even stronger. Why even bother? Or or say it
another way, why did the פסוק pasuk bother to indicate that to
me if I could have figured it out by myself? Okay. And
then if you look at the last three lines, he says, יש
לחלק דיש דברים שאין הסברא פשוטה כל כך וצריך פסוק לאשמיענו הסברא.
Yesh lachaleik d'yesh devarim she-ein ha-svara peshutah kol kach v'tzarich pasuk l'ashmi'einu
ha-svara. Sometimes the logic is not compelling by itself. So then I
need a פסוק pasuk to sort of indicate to me, yes, this
logic that you might have been wavering about, that's the right way
of thinking about it. That's actually a good example right here, because
here the סברא svara was not so compelling. Okay, the פסוק pasuk
was more compelling. Alright, so let's take a look now as we
continue in the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so we've anyway
made the point that אכילה, achilah, the word אכילה achilah includes drinking,
and now we're going to say, yes, that's pretty obvious from our
משנה. mishna. Okay. אמר רבא אתן נמי תנינא, Amar Rava atan nami
tanina, we also taught similarly in our משנה. mishna. שבועה שלא אוכל
ואכל ושתה אינו חייב אלא אחת. Shvuah shelo ochel v'achal v'shasah eino
chayav ela achas.
If you say a שבועה shvuah that you won't eat and you
eat and drink, you only get one קרבן. korban. אי אמרת בשלמא
משתייה בכלל אכילה איתיה, Ei amart bishlama mashtya bikhlal achilah itya, drinking
would be considered a violation of the שבועה shvuah and included in
'I won't eat', איצטריך ליה למתני לאשמועינן דאינו חייב אלא אחת. itztrich
lei l'masni l'ashmu'einan d'eino chayav ela achas. So it had to tell
you, although you did these two separate violations, one by eating and
one by drinking, it's only one קרבן. korban. אלא אי אמרת שתייה
לאו בכלל אכילה, Ela ei amart shtiyah lav bikhlal achilah, but if
drinking wasn't included in, would not have been included in your words
'I won't eat' and would not have been a violation, so אכילה
שבועה שלא אוכל ואכל ועשה מלאכה מי איצטריך לאשמועינן דאינו חייב אלא
אחת? achilah shvuah shelo ochel v'achal v'asah melachah mi itztrich l'ashmu'einan d'eino
chayav ela achas?
Let's say the guy said a שבועה shvuah 'I won't eat', and
then he goes and he eats and he scratches his back. Oh,
you only bring one קרבן. korban. Of course you only bring one
קרבן. korban. Scratching your back wasn't included in your שבועה. shvuah. So
רבא Rava says, if drinking wasn't included in the שבועה, shvuah, he
wouldn't have to say, if you eat and drink, you only bring
one קרבן. korban. He said if you eat and you drive your
car, you only bring one קרבן. korban. Of course! Clearly the fact
that he had to say it is because שתייה shtiyah is a
violation of the שבועה, shvuah, and nevertheless, because it's one שבועה, shvuah,
you only bring one קרבן. korban.
Then we move the other way around, but I said, alright, you
know, I swear I won't drink.
Right, eating is not included in drinking, drinking is included in eating.
Okay, so where
was I? אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye says,
אלא מאי שתייה בכלל אכילה? ela mai shtiyah bikhlal achilah?
So you want to say, okay, so let's work with this. Yes,
you're right, פשט pshat of the משנה, mishna, שתייה shtiyah is included
on אכילה. achilah. אימא סיפא, Eima seifa, let's keep on reading. שבועה
שלא אוכל ושלא אשתה, Shvuah shelo ochel v'shelo eshteh, if a guy
says 'I won't eat and I won't drink', ואכל ושתה, v'achal v'shasah,
then he eats and drinks, so that's two separate שבועות shvuos and
חייב שתים, chayav shtayim, it's two separate sins and he brings two
קרבנות. korbanos. So one minute, says אביי, Abaye, כיון דאמר שלא אוכל,
keivan d'amar shelo ochel, as he's getting the words out of his
mouth, he says 'a שבועה shvuah I won't eat'. As soon as
he, before he gets to the second part of the statement, 'and
won't drink', those words 'won't eat', איתסר ליה בשתייה, issar lei bi-shtiyah,
already prevent him from drinking,
right? Because as soon as he says 'I won't eat', it means
I won't eat or drink. So then כי אמר שלא אשתה, ki
amar shelo eshteh, when he finishes his sentence and says 'and won't
drink', so אמאי חייב? amai chayav? Why does that create a separate
prohibition on him? Alright, so we will see that. אילו אמר שלא
אשתה תרי זימני, Ilu amar shelo eshteh trei zimni, let's say he
said 'I won't drink, I won't drink', מי חייב תרתי? mi chayav
tartei? That's not two קרבנות, korbanos, that's only one קרבן. korban. That's
the principle of אין שבועה חלה על שבועה. ein shvuah chalah al
shvuah. So if a שבועה shvuah already prohibited this, so he had
one global שבועה shvuah 'won't eat' which means eat and drink, so
the second שבועה shvuah doesn't take effect. And then when he eats
and drinks, he's only violating the first part of the שבועה. shvuah.
The second one never took effect. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so רבא
Rava said back to him, התם דאמר שלא אשתה והדר אמר שלא
אוכל. hasam d'amar shelo eshteh v'hadar amar shelo ochel. No, no, no,
the משנה's mishna being a little imprecise. The order he said his
sentence was reversed. The guy said a שבועה shvuah that he won't
drink and I won't eat.
And therefore, the drinking was first prohibited by itself, and then the
eating was the bigger שבועה. shvuah. דשתייה בכלל אכילה איתא
אכילה בכלל שתייה ליתא. de-shtiyah bikhlal achilah isa, achilah bikhlal shtiyah leisa.
Because yes, שתייה shtiyah is included in
אכילה, achilah, but eating is not included in drinking. When the guy
says 'won't drink', that just means drinking. Okay, so רבא Rava answers
this question by reversing the order of the sentence. So the גמרא
Gemara says, אבל אמר שבועה שלא אוכל ושלא אשתה ואכל ושתה מאי
אינו חייב אלא אחת? aval amar shvuah shelo ochel v'shelo eshteh v'achal
v'shasah mai, eino chayav ela achas? So אביי Abaye says back to
him, okay fine, but you're conceding my point. You would say that
if the guy actually said 'I won't eat and I won't drink',
then eating includes both and it's one שבועה, shvuah, and the second
part 'I won't drink' never takes effect, and therefore if he does
both he'd only bring one
קרבן. korban. אי הכי, Ei hachi, if that's true, אדקתני רישא שבועה
שלא אוכל ואכל ושתה אינו חייב אלא אחת, ad-katani reisha shvuah shelo
ochel v'achal v'shasah eino chayav ela achas, when it told us the
guy when it gave... it told us if the guy says 'I
won't eat' and he eats and drinks, it's only one קרבן. korban.
So okay, that's a certain level of a חידוש, chiddush, but ליתני,
lisni, there's a bigger חידוש chiddush you could have told us. שבועה
שלא אוכל ושלא אשתה, Shvuah shelo ochel v'shelo eshteh, if the guy
says 'I won't eat and I won't drink', it should have said
אינו חייב אלא אחת, eino chayav ela achas, then it's only one
קרבן korban because of this idea that the drinking didn't take effect
because it was
all... And actually wrong. Right.
אלא *ella*, well right, meaning our
משנה Mishnah.
*mishnah* is imprecise and actually wrong. Right. אלא לעולם כדקתני *ella le'olam
kidkasni*. Fine, fine, fine. Okay, it's like he said. He says I
won't eat and won't drink. So how do we answer the question?
Why don't we say that the drinking never took effect? So this
is now what Michael said, ושאני הכא Hacha, *v'shani hacha*. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* should just consult with Michael, then we would have
a much more boring גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. ושאני הכא *v'shani hacha*, כיון
דאמר D'amar, שלא אוכל והדר אמר שלא אשתה *keivan d'amar shelo ochal
v'hadar amar shelo eshteh*, because we look at what the word אוכל
*ochal* means in context. אוכל *ochal* by itself, you know, means eating
and drinking, all forms of consuming food. Okay, but if a guy
said won't eat and won't drink, in that context, eating just means
solid food, and drinking means liquids. Okay. כיון דאמר שלא אוכל והדר
אמר שלא אשתה גלי אדעתיה דהך אכילה דאמר אכילה גרידתא היא *keivan
d'amar shelo ochal v'hadar amar shelo eshteh gali adatei de'hach achilah d'amar
achilah geridasa hi*. That's אכילה *achilah* defined narrowly. Okay, so in this
context, אכילה *achilah* just means eating and not eating and drinking. The
question is, right, how much what would you need to define context?
Right? Is it because he says it תוך כדי דיבור *toch k'dei
dibur*, but if he said it a minute later? What if it's
like הסוגיה באותו עניין *hasugya b'oso inyan*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is not interested in that question right now, but it is an
important question. Right? How much what do you look at to defining
context? Right? But anyway, but it says there are contexts where obviously
the word אכילה *achilah* just means eating and not eating and drinking.
All right. אמר רב אשי Rav Ashi *Amar Rav Ashi*, מתניתין נמי
דייקא *masnisin nami deika*, going back to proving that אכילה *achilah* includes
drinking. Our משנה Mishnah *mishnah* also, if it דייקא *deika* means like
a close textual read of our משנה Mishnah. *mishnah* bears this out.
שבועה שלא אוכל Shvua she-lo ochel, *Shvua shelo ochal*, a guy says
a שבועה shvua *shvua* he won't eat, ואכל אוכלין שאינם ראוים לאכילה
ושתה משקין שאינם ראוים לשתיה פטור patur. *v'achal ochlin she'einam ruyim l'achilah
v'shasa mashkin she'einam ruyim l'shisiyah patur*, and he eats food that's unfit
for consumption or drinks drinks that are unfit for drinking, he's exempt.
הראוין חייב chayav, *ha'ruyim chayav*, if any of those were fit for
consumption, he would transgress. So including if he drank drinks that were
fit for consumption he would transgress. דאמאי השבועה שלא אוכל קאמר *d'amai
hashvua shelo ochal ka'amar*, he says a שבועה shvua *shvua* that I
won't eat.
So clearly eating includes drinking. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, nah,
you can get out of it. You could say the משנה Mishna,
*mishnah*'s being a little abbreviated. דילמא דאמר תרתי שבועה שלא אוכל Shvua
she-lo ochel. ושבועה שלא אשתה *dilma d'amar tarti shvua shelo ochal v'shvua
shelo eshteh*. Maybe, you know, when it's talking there about drinking, it's
implying that you took a שבועה shvua, *shvua* that you won't drink
and telling you, and by the way, if you drink things that
are not fit for drinking, you don't transgress. All right. So anyway,
you know, maybe you can't prove it 100% from the משנה Mishna
*mishnah*. Hold on, I'm sorry, this dust is getting in my eyes.
Maybe you can't prove it 100% from the משנה Mishna, *mishnah*, but
certainly the simple sense of the משנה *mishnah* is, and the ruling
is, that eating includes drinking, and when but when you say eat
and drink, in that context, eat just refers to eating solid food.
Okay. Now we get to the next part of the משנה *mishnah*.
The next part of the משנה *mishnah* is, the guy says I
won't eat bread of, you know, wheat and spelt and barley, that's
three separate שבועות shvuos. *shvuos*. Now what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* asks
is, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes that we only divide that into
three שבועות shvuos. *shvuos* if there was an alternative way of saying
that in a way that would have bundled them up more as
one unit. And because you didn't bundle them as one unit and
you identified them as separate things, then therefore we treat it as
three separate שבועות shvuos *shvuos*.
He would have said like, I שבועה shvua. *shvua* I won't eat
grain products or something?
Something like that. Okay, but the problem is, says the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*, there's not always a way to bundle it up in one
thing, because grain products would have also included rye and spelt or
whatever, the other things. So the only way that I could refer
to these things and not other things was by naming them. So
now you could say, tough luck. The הלכה *halacha* of the שבועה
shvua. *shvua* is, even if you had no alternatives, if you name
different acts or you name different products, even if there was no
other way of saying it, those are considered separate שבועות shvuos. *shvuos*.
That's just the הלכה *halacha*. You could have said that. But the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't say that. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says we
only divide those as separate שבועות shvuos *shvuos* if there was an
alternative to bundle them together. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says, there's
not always cases that you could have bundled them together, the cases
in the משנה *mishnah*. How else would you have said these three
types of bread? Okay. So let's take a look at the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, שבועה shvua שלא אוכל
ואכל פת pas. חיטין ודילמא למפטרי נפשיה מאחרנייתא קאתי *shvua shelo ochal
v'achal pas chitin v'dilma l'miftei nafshai m'achranyaisa ka'asi*. Maybe the reason he's
labeling these three is not to create three separate שבועות shvuos. *shvuos*,
but to say these three types of bread and not others. Okay.
הוה ליה למימר חיטים ושעורין וכוסמין *hava lei l'meimar chitin u'seorin v'chusmin*.
He shouldn't have said פת pas. חיטין *pas chitin*, bread of wheat,
bread of, he just should have said wheat, barley, and spelt. גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, but that would have been a different שבועה shvua.
*shvua*. ודילמא לכוסי *v'dilma l'chosei*, that would have referred to not eating
bread, that would have referred to chewing the, you know, the flour
or the grain itself. He had to say the word bread, he's
referring to bread. Okay. הוה ליה למימר פת pas? חיטים ושעורין וכוסמין
*hava lei l'meimar pas chitin u'seorin v'chusmin*. I won't eat bread of
wheat, barley, or spelt. And therefore, because he put in the extra
word פת *pas*, bread of wheat, bread of spelt, bread of barley,
that separated them into three separate שבועות shvuot, *shvuos*. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, no, that would not have been as clear. ודילמא
פת חיטין *v'dilma pas chitin*, I would have read that as, I
won't eat bread of wheat, comma, spelt or barley, I won't eat
spelt and I won't eat barley. Okay, but if he said פת
חטים chitim לאכול, I won't eat bread of wheat, שעורים וכוסמין לכסוס,
seorim u'kusmim lekhasos, and I won't chew on barley or spelt. So
I needed the word bread to be clear.
Okay. דהוה ליה למימר, dehavei leh l'meimar, he could have said פת
חטים ושל שעורין ושל כוסמין. pas chitim v'shel seorin v'shel kusmin. I
won't eat bread of wheat or of spelt or of barley. Okay,
and I could so now it's not really doesn't really save you
any words. The word של shel is just as big of a
word as the word פת. My brother used to laugh, you know,
when they would give you the traffic report. They would sort of
say, oh you know, whatever, there's like a 20-minute delay on the
GWB. So he says, you realize GWB is just as many syllables
as George Washington Bridge. So okay, but anyway, so the word של
shel is just as many syllables and just as many letters as
the word פת. But nevertheless the גמרא Gemara said that would have
bundled them more clearly. It's not a shorter way of speaking, but
it would have bundled them more clearly: bread of wheat, of spelt,
of barley. So that would have bundled it together. Since you said
bread of wheat, bread of spelt, bread of barley, that at least
is some distinction that we can say separates them a little bit
more, that we'll treat it as three separate שבועות. shvuos Okay, ושל
כוסמין. v'shel kusmin. So the גמרא Gemara says, ודילמא על ידי תערובת?
v'dilema al yedei taaroves? No, no, no. If I would have said
I won't eat bread of wheat, of wheat and of spelt and
of barley, I might have thought it meant I won't eat some
bread made of all those three grains mixed together. Even if I
would have said the word of, because that would have bundled them
more, I would have said it meant a bread of mixed grain.
So אימא וכן של שעורים וכן של כוסמין. eima v'chein shel seorim
v'chein shel kusmin. So now you actually have to use even more
words, right? You could have said I won't eat bread of wheat
and similarly of barley and similarly of spelt. So that's a lot
more words, but at least that would have made it clear that
you meant it as a unit. So the גמרא Gemara does not
need there to be an alternative that is just as easy to
say. But what it needs to say is that this way of
phrasing it this way because there is some alternative that would have
grouped them more, this way makes them separate and therefore separate שבועות.
shvuos. Okay,
פת פת למה לי? pas pas lama li? Why repeat the word
פת? And again the answer that it's shorter is not a good
answer. שמע מינה לחלק, shma mina l'chaleik, that makes that shows that
they're separate. So again the גמרא Gemara is sort of saying we
will not define something, even though logically any normal person would rather
just say פת פת פת, pas pas pas, okay, and he still
might mean in his I don't think at the end of the
day we're doing what's in his mind, okay, because in his mind
he might mean to think of this as one big שבועה shvua.
and he's just saying פת פת פת pas pas pas because it's
shorter. Okay, so it's not really what's in his mind. It's more
point like we halachically, forget what's in his mind, we halachically can't
divide this and call this three separate שבועות shvuos, if there was
if we see that this is the exact way you would say
it even if you meant it as one unit. If there's out
there another way you could have said it to have meant to
have meant it as one unit, okay, then we will look at
this way as defining separate units. Okay, so that's why the גמרא
Gemara has to say there is some way to say it, you
know, that could have meant we're looking at it as one big
שבועה shvua. and all of us together, and therefore because it's said
this way even though the other way was much more, you know,
sort of verbose, because we said it this way because it's phrased
this way, that allows us to say this sort of puts things
in separate silos and this allows us to treat it as separate
שבועות. shvuos. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, and
now we're going to continue though, we have to continue doing this
throughout the משנה. And the next part of the משנה is the
guy said I won't drink wine or oil or honey. Now what's
how else could you talk about that in one as one big
שבועה, shvua right? There's no separate words to distinguish those things and
we still treat those as three שבועות shvuos and not as one
שבועה. shvua. בשלמא התם דאמרת מייתר
ליה פת
פת לחיובא. bishlama hasam d'amart miyater leh pas pas l'chiyuva. I got
our earlier discussion. You said the word bread of this, bread of
that was enough to identify them as separate as separate, you know,
silos and therefore separate שבועות. shvuot אלא הכא מאי הוה ליה למימר?
ela hacha mai hava leh l'meimar? Here there's no alternative way to
speak, right? You said I won't drink wine or bread or wine
or oil or honey. So that's how you define those three and
not other liquids. So what defines that as separate as a separate
oath? Okay. ודילמא למעוטי
שאר משקין הוא דאתא? v'dilema l'mautei sh'ar mashkin hu d'ata? Maybe he's
just doing that just to say that he that it's okay for
him to drink other liquids. אמר רב פפא הכא במונחים לפניו עסקינן.
amar Rav Papa hacha bimunachim lefanav askinan. Okay, what we're talking about
is right in front of you on the table you have wine
and honey and oil. And then you have an alternative. You could
say I'm not going to drink any of these three products, right?
And that would have clearly made it clear that you just meant
that as one big שבועה. shvua שהיה לו לומר שבועה
שלא אשתה
אלו. shehaya lo lomar shvua shelo eshteh eilu. The guy could have
said a שבועה shvua I won't drink any of these things. Okay,
and because he identified wine, honey, and
oil. No, if he just said, "I won't drink these three," it
means I won't drink the concrete specific three things in front of
me. It doesn't mean I won't drink wine in general or honey
in general. Okay, that would not have been what he wanted to
say. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא דאמר ela deamar fine, here's
what he could have said: שבועה דלא שתינא כגון
אלו. shvua delo shatina kegon elu. I'm not going to drink anything
like these. Okay? So, and that would have included all, you know,
all wine, all honey. גמרא Gemara says no, דילמא כגון אלו דלא
שתינא בציר מהכי וטפי מהכי שתינא. dilma kegon elu delo shatina batzir
mehachi vetafei mehachi shatina. Like these might have meant these amounts. I
won't drink a cup of wine exactly like this. Maybe a little
less, a little more I will drink. אלא כגון דאמר שבועה שלא
אשתה ממין
אלו. ela kegon deamar shvua shelo eshteh mimen elu. Okay, he's more
specific. He could have said, "I won't drink anything of these types
of liquids." Okay, that's pretty clear. All right? Now again, it takes
much more words maybe, but there's a better way to say it
if, you know, that would have made them one unit rather than
separate units. "I won't drink any of these types of liquids." ודילמא
ממין אלו הוא דלא שתינא האינהו גופייהו
שתינא. vedilma mimen elu hu delo shatina haneihu gufayhu shatina. I don't
get exactly this question. Maybe I won't drink any of these types
of liquids, but these liquids themselves I will drink, which I don't
understand. The wine in front of me is still a type of
this liquid. But anyway, I don't really get this question. Anyway the
גמרא Gemara says, fine, כגון דאמר kegon deamar fine, אימא שלא אשתה
אלו וממיניהם. eima shelo eshte elu umimineihem. I won't drink these or
anything of their types. So you could have said that and that
would have bundled it all together as one שבועה. shvua And since,
even though it would have been much more pain in the neck
to say, but since you said it in a way wine and
oil and honey, that at least lets everything stand by itself and
therefore it's a separate שבועה. shvua So what gets clear in the
גמרא, Gemara again I cannot imagine that the גמרא thinks that we're
getting into this guy's mindset because everything he said here was the
easier thing to say. But what it's sort of saying is halachically
we are not able, yes, there's a basic principle if you say
different objects or different acts we define them as different שבועות, shvuot.
but we're not able to do that unless there was some way,
even if it would have been not a normal thing anybody would
have done, but unless there would have been some way to have
framed this in a way that would have bundled them more together.
And if there's a way to frame it that would have bundled
them more together, then because you labeled them as you did, we're
going to define it as each one is a separate שבועה. shvua
Okay. רב אחא בריה דרב איקא אמר במוסר לו חברו אשכחן. Rav
Acha brei deRav Ika amar bemosar lo chaveiro ashkechan. And here's the
way in which we can say why we treat it, why there
was an easier way or not an easier, excuse me, an alternative
way to say it that would have bundled it together. One example
we gave was that they were on the table. This example is
that somebody is pressuring you to do this. במסי ר לו חברו
אשכחן. bemosar lo chaveiro ashkechan. דאמר לו, deamar lo, "בוא שתה מיין
ושמן ודבש. bo shete miyayin veshemen udevash. Come on Gloria, let's go.
We're going to go to a whole big drinking party. We'll have,
there will be wine and oil and honey. Anyway, come drink with
me." And you say, "No, no, no." "Yes, come, come, it'll be
great." דהוה ליה למימר, dehavah leih lemimar, where Gloria should have said
then is, or could have said, it would have
been, שבועה שלא אשתה עמך. shvua shelo eshte imcha. A שבועה shvua
I won't have any drink with you. Okay? יין ושמן ודבש למה
לי? yayin veshemen udevash lamah li? Why did you have to say
wine and oil and honey? לחיובא על כל אחת ואחת. lechiyuva al
kol achat veachat. That shows each one. Now of course if she
would have said, "I swear I won't drink with you," it only
would have meant for this particular party. It wouldn't have meant never
drink wine and oil. But רב אשי's Rav Ashi, understanding, it's רב
אשי, right? No, רב אחא בריה דרב איקא Rav Acha brei deRav
Ika is understanding that that's the context of the משנה. That even
when Gloria says wine and honey and oil, in this context it
just means at this party. Okay? So therefore if you're just talking
about what you're going to drink at this party and whatever, you
could have said it much easier. You could have said it in
a way that would have bundled it all together. And because you
identified each one, that at least in this example it took more
effort to identify each one. And because it took more effort to
identify each one, we're going to say that each one is a
separate שבועה. shvua I don't know if in general רב אחא Rav
Acha requires that, that it's only seen as separate when that required
more effort, but anyway he gives that as the case that we're
dealing with. All right. Yes, Gloria?
"And how do you in general know what the duration of the
שבועה shvua. is? How do you know that it's today or at
the..."
"Yeah, that is a really good question and that's, you know, as
true by שבועה shvua, and it's true by נדרים. nedarim. Like we
go by, there's a general principle that עד שיהא פיו ולבו שוים.
ad sheyehe piv velibo shavim. You know, you have to, your mind
and your speech have to be in sync. Right? That's like an
old line, right? What is it, you know, don't put your mouth
in drive until you put your brain in gear.
I just didn't put my brain in gear right there. Anyway, so,
you know, and therefore which is a basic principle that we don't,
you don't just go by formally what you say. It has to
be what you meant. Right? And then it's a little strict about
we don't always know what you meant and sometimes we have to
give a legal definition to the scope of your words because you
weren't exactly thinking how much food do I need, how much whatever.
Right? But anyway..." But yeah, so to some degree we would look
at context, and to some degree תוספות Tosafot even talks about sometimes
maybe we would even ask you. We would say, what were you
intending? Were you intending today, were you intending at this
party? You know, if you take a quick look and you want
to see just quickly back because it makes a very important point,
it's like a one-line תוספות. Tosafot.
Let me see if I can find it. Yeah, on
כף עמוד א, Kaf Amud Aleph,
you know, I don't know if you have to look at it,
but לישנא דאיתקלי, Lishna Itkelei, תוספות Tosafot just says, I'll just read
you one line: ואם תאמר נשאליה מאי היה בדעתו. Ve-im tomar nishaleh
mai hayah bedato. Okay,
so top of the page of כף עמוד א, Kaf Amud Aleph,
לישנא דאיתקלי, Lishna Itkelei, like the first narrow line of the תוספות.
Tosafot. נשאליה מאי היה בדעתו, Nishaleh mai hayah bedato, let's just ask
him what he was thinking, and let his report of what he
was thinking tell us what the scope of his words was. And
תוספות's Tosafot answer for that case was, well, he says, I wasn't
thinking anything in particular, I
was thinking whatever the rabbis will tell me the legal meaning of
this word is. Okay, but it's very important that he basically says
that that is an option, to ask the person. All right, so
sometimes we would try to look at context, sometimes maybe we would
ask the person, but yeah, it's not always obvious what the answer
is. You know, lacking context and lacking either asking the person or
trusting what the person is telling us, then we might interpret it
in its most expansive definition, which would be, you know, very onerous.
Okay, let's take a look now but that's a very good question,
very important question. Let's look now at the גמרא continues.
Is it valid a oath if you didn't somebody doesn't really know
what they intend to mean by it?
Well,
I'm not sure what you mean, like I
mean, are they liable for something when they don't even know what
they're saying so to speak?
Well, what did they think they were saying?
Right, like we were saying here in this case the fellow's response
was I don't really know what I meant.
Well, but then he is liable, because then he intends it to
mean what implicitly he's okay with whatever the legal meaning is that
is given to what he said, you know. I mean, there are
cases where you're making an oath and it was in error, and
rather than saying you
transgressed בשוגג, bishogeg, we say, you know, like if you think you're
telling the truth and you're lying, right, then it's not really even
a violate we'll get to that. Okay, but anyway. All right, so
let's take a look at the גמרא says like this, תנן התם,
Tnan hatam, we taught over there, later in our פרק, perek, or
in a later פרק, perek, excuse me. תן לי חטים ושעורים וכוסמין
שיש לי בידך. Ten li chitin u-seorim u-kusmin sheyesh li beyadecha. Now
when you're dealing not with a
שבועת ביטוי shvuat bituy like a שבועה shvua about the past just
for its own sake, like a guy swears that he had so
and so for breakfast, or שבועה shvua about the future, but it's
a שבועה shvua in the context of litigation and you're telling me
you borrowed from me a thousand dollars and you say no I
didn't and I say take an oath for me, okay? And if
you take a false oath, then, you know, you're חייב, chayav you
transgress, and there you transgress as opposed to the principle of אין
שבועה חלה על שבועה, ein shvua chal al shvua, right, which is
also mostly future oriented, I won't eat this and then you repeat
it a second time as we've just said, you only bring one
קרבן, korban, you don't bring a קרבן korban for every separate שבועה
shvua because you're already forsworn, okay, when you take a שבועה shvua.
in the context of litigation about the past and about whether you
basically owe somebody money or whatever and you're lying, you are חייב
chayav. separately for every separate שבועה. shvua Okay, so that's one thing
you have to know. So let's take a look now at this
משנה, okay? Or so the משנה says the following. Right. Right. And
those are also separate קרבנות korbanot and אשם גזלות, asham gezelot, when
you basically use an oath to swear and to effectively steal from
somebody because through your oath you're denying a debt, okay, so that
would also bring a קרבן, korban, but there you bring separate קרבנות,
korbanot, not a standard חטאת, chatat, an אשם, asham, but you bring
separate קרבנות korbanot for every separate שבועה, shvua even if it's repeating
yourself. Okay, so let's take a look. So the גמרא says like
this: תנן התם תן לי חטים ושעורים וכוסמין, Tnan hatam: ten li
chitin u-seorim u-kusmin, you know, I go ahead and say to ראובן,
Reuven, hey, give me all that wheat and barley and spelt שיש
לי בידך sheyesh li beyadecha that I gave you, I gave you
a five pound bag of wheat and a five pound bag of
barley, five pound bag of spelt, give it back to me. שבועה
שאין לך בידי כלום, Shvua she-ein lecha beyadi klum, I take an
oath I don't owe you anything. אינו חייב אלא אחת, Eino chayav
ela achat, and he's lying, he brings one אשם, asham, one קרבן.
korban. שבועה שאין לך בידי חטים ושעורים וכוסמין. Shvua she-ein lecha beyadi
chitin u-seorim u-kusmin. Now, again, to repeat, if he had said שבועה
shvua I don't owe you anything, שבועה shvua I don't owe you
anything, שבועה shvua I don't owe you anything, he would bring three
קרבנות, korbanot, as opposed to what we're learning about שבועת ביטוי shvuat
bituy of אין שבועה חלה על שבועה. ein shvua chal al shvua.
In that case of litigation, if you repeat yourself or you're redundant,
it's still a separate קרבן. korban. Okay, so if he says I
don't owe you anything, one קרבן. korban. If he says I don't
have of yours neither wheat, nor barley, nor spelt, חייב. chayav חייב
על כל אחת ואחת. chayav al kol achas v'achas. Then that's three
separate קרבנות. korbanos. Same idea. We divide that because he named the
objects separately and we consider that three separate שבועות and he's lying
about all of them, so he brings three קרבנות. korbanos. דאמר רבי
יוחנן, D'amar Reb Yochanan, אפילו פרוטה מכאן מצטרפת. afilu pruta mikam mitztarefes.
Now, you're only חייב chayav if through your שבועה shvua. you are
denying a penny's worth, a פרוטה'ס pruta's worth of value. So let's
say basically I am denying with my oath a half of a
פרוטה'ס pruta's worth of wheat and a half of a פרוטה'ס pruta's
worth of barley. Okay, so since in the total I am denying
a פרוטה'ס pruta's worth, then I'm חייב chayav for my oath. All
right, but there's the problem. If my oath was I don't owe
you anything and I owe you a half a penny worth of
wheat and a half a penny worth of barley, then I transgressed
that oath because I owe you a penny and I said I
don't owe you anything. But if I say I don't owe you
wheat and I don't owe you barley and I don't owe you
spelt and I owe you a half a penny of wheat and
a half a penny of barley, I haven't transgressed either שבועה. shvua
Right, you get it? Because if I haven't owed you wheat, it
would require for me to transgress that a penny's worth of wheat
and I only owe you a half penny's worth. Okay, so let's
see how we figure this out. Okay, because the presumably the reason
you bring three קרבנות korbanos is when I say wheat, barley, and
spelt, it's three separate שבועות. But it's three separate שבועות, how does
a half penny of wheat combine with a half penny of spelt?
All right, so אפילו פרוטה מכאן מצטרפת. afilu pruta mikam mitztarefes. פליגי
בה רב אחא ורבינא. Pleigi bah Rav Acha v'Ravina. רב אחא ורבינא
Rav Acha v'Ravina debate this. חד אמר אפרטי מיחייב אכללי לא מיחייב.
Chad amar a'prati mechayiv a'klali lo mechayiv. So one says when I
say שבועה shvua. that I don't owe you wheat, barley, and spelt,
then I actually bring and I'm lying, I actually would bring four
קרבנות. korbanos. You know why? Because I basically defined, right, it says
שבועה שאין לך בידי חטים שעורים וכוסמין. shvua she'ein lcha beyadi chitim
se'orim v'kusmin. So he reads this as: this is שבועה shvua number
one, I don't owe you anything, and שבועה shvua number two, I
don't owe you wheat, שבועה shvua number three, I don't owe you
barley, שבועה shvua number four, I don't owe you spelt. We defined
this as four שבועות. Okay. And therefore that's one version, okay. And
therefore if I'm lying and I owe you a lot of that
stuff, I would bring four קרבנות. korbanos. The other approach, what
is it? My... I cannot
believe all my stuff goes missing. It's just isn't in place. You
know what I'm going to do, I'm going to get a lockbox
by the Ozier. Okay, the other one says no, this is just
the first part is just a... it's not yet a statement. It
doesn't yet exist as its own שבועה. shvua This type of a
case is only three שבועות and there's not one global one that
we read into it. Okay, so that's the debate when you say
you're חייב chayav for each one, do we read this as a
global or do we read this as only the specific? פליגי בה
רב אחא ורבינא. Pleigi bah Rav Acha v'Ravina. חד אמר אפרטי מיחייב,
Chad amar a'prati mechayiv, you're חייב chayav only for the specifics, אכללי
לא מיחייב, a'klali lo mechayiv, you're not חייב chayav for the general.
וחד אמר אכללי נמי מיחייב. V'chad amar a'klali nami mechayiv. You're also
for the... you're also חייב chayav for the general. Now of course
if you're חייב chayav for the general, we would understand רבי יוחנן
Reb Yochanan why he would say a half cent here plus a
half cent here combine, because at least it combines to be מחייב
mechayiv you for the general one, even though it doesn't... even though
it's not... even though it doesn't combine across you know because you
still aren't חייב chayav now for חטים and you're not חייב chayav
for שעורים, se'orim, there was only a half pennies of each. But
you are חייב chayav for the top one. Okay, it does not
explain why it would combine if you keep them in separate silos.
All right, but anyway, okay. So then based on that, there's a...
so according to the idea that these are separate when you say
it this way, the statement that the half פרוטות prutos combine only
go by the first statement. The first one was remember שבועה אין
לך בידי כלום shvua ein lcha beyadi klum when there was only
one. So when רבי יוחנן Reb Yochanan says half pennies combine, according
to the version here that you only have the specifics, his statement
that half pennies combine was referring to this case. When you just
said I don't owe you anything, then as long as there's a
total penny's worth, it doesn't matter if it's across different types because
you only have the global. Okay, if you say that in this
case however this is four types of oaths, okay, one, two, three,
four, then the half pennies can even combine here for the... for
the top oath, for the global one. All right, so that's that
debate. But what's important for us is to notice that in this
type of a case there's an opinion that defines this as four
oaths. So we want to know what about for our case? If
a guy says a שבועה shvua that I won't drink, you know,
wine and blah blah blah blah blah and then he does all
the things, does he bring if he says wine and oil and
honey, does he bring three קרבנות korbanos or does he just bring?
Okay, so the גמרא says like this: So הכא מאי? hacha mai?
What would be the story here? אמר רבא, Amar Rava, maybe here
also there should be a general plus specifics. הכי השתא? Hachi hashta?
What type of a question is that? התם מחייב אכלל ומחייב אפרטא.
Hatam mechayev a-klal u-mechayev a-prata. In that case, it's possible to say
that you transgress for the general statement and for the specifics. דאי
מישתבע והדר מישתבע מחייב תרתי. De-i mishtava ve-hadar mishtava mechayev tartei. Because
remember, if you took the same oath twice, you'd bring two קרבנות.
korbanot. Right? הכא, but here, אי סלקא דעתך איכא בכלל ופרט, ei
salka daitach ika be-klal u-ferat, if you were to read the sentence
as a general and then specifics, אמאי מחייב? amai mechayev? Why are
you חייב chayav. for the specifics? מושבע ועומד הוא. Mushba ve-omed hu.
You've already made it forbidden by your initial שבועה. shvua Right? If
the guy says, שבועה שלא אשתה יין ושמן ודבש. Shvua she-lo eshteh
yayin ve-shemen u-devash. Okay, if you want to define this as four
שבועות because you want to see maybe we'll get the guy to
bring four קרבנות korbanot if he does all those things. But when
but if this is if this is a general and it it
means all these three, then you never get around to having these
taking effect. Right? Because because in our case once there's a שבועה
shvua about the future, the rest is מושבע ועומד. mushba ve-omed. Right?
Here, I've been telling you that you can make the same שבועה
shvua multiple times and bring multiple קרבנות. korbanot. So it doesn't matter
that these are if this is a general that these are redundant.
It would still bring multiple קרבנות. korbanot. But in this case, if
something is redundant, it doesn't take effect. Okay, when it's future-oriented about
what you are going to do. So therefore Rava says clearly we
do not read this as a general statement, we only read these
as specifics because if we were to read this as general, the
specifics would not take effect. But it also doesn't even sound like
a general. Right, it's not I'm not going to drink. I was
thinking about that too. As you say שבועה אין לך בידי shvua
ein lecha be-yadi after the guy said you owe me חיטין ושעורין
וכוסמין, chitin u-seorin u-chusmin, that stands by itself. Right? Even before you
get to the details. I agree with you as well. But I
guess Rava's point is even if I could construct a case where
it would be able to exist by itself, we wouldn't read it
that way because by reading it that way, we are eliminating the
the specific שבועות. But yes, I I completely agree with you. Okay,
so let's we have a few more minutes, let's just get a
little bit further. שבועה shvua שלא אוכל, okay? So now because this
is going to be a repeat what we saw before. The guy
takes an oath not to eat, it includes tref food. Tref food
is considered eating. Okay, but the גמרא's going to be דייק dayek
with him. A, why is it eating? You're not allowed to eat
it. There you can distinguish between physically able to eat and being
prohibited to eat. And B is the question about what do you
call it? About aren't you מושבע ועומד? mushba ve-omed? Why does the
שבועה shvua take effect? You're already forbidden to eat that. Okay. שבועה
shvua שלא אוכל. הגופא קשיא. Ha gufa kashya. One minute, this doesn't
make sense. אמרת שבועה שלא אוכל ואכל אוכלים שאינם ראויים לאכילה ושתה
משקים שאינם ראויים לשתיה פטור. Amarta shvua she-lo ochel ve-achal ochlin she-einam
reuyin la-achila ve-shata mashkin she-einam reuyin li-shtiya patur. If you eat stuff
that's not edible, you're פטור. patur והדר תני שבועה שלא אוכל ואכל
נבילות וטריפות שקצים ורמשים חייב. Ve-hadar tanyi shvua she-lo ochel ve-achal nevelot
u-treifot shekatzim u-remashim chayav. And then it says if you eat non-kosher
food, חייב. chayav You transgress. מאי שנא רישא דפטור ומאי שנא סיפא
דחייב? Mai shna reisha de-patur u-mai shna seifa de-chayav? What's the difference,
why are you פטור in the beginning and חייב here? Non-kosher food
isn't edible. Now the obvious answer the גמרא should have said, which
the גמרא actually did say earlier is, it is edible. It's just
forbidden. There's a difference between whether the תורה Torah forbids you or
whether from a physical perspective it's edible. Okay, the גמרא could have
said that. The גמרא says something else. הא לא קשיא רישא בסתם
וסיפא במפרש. Ha lo kashya reisha bi-stam ve-seifa bi-meforesh. Now, the רישא
reisha is when you just say I won't eat. So I won't
eat only means edible things and maybe the גמרא suggests here, which
is not at all פשט pshat of the משנה, maybe that would
exclude non-kosher food. Maybe you're right, maybe if all you said was
I won't eat, that eating non-kosher food is considered inedible. But the
end is a case where you explicitly said, a שבועה shvua that
I won't eat, you know, חזיר. chazir. Okay, so if you're explicit,
then it includes that type of thing. You could say the guy
could say a שבועה shvua he won't eat dirt. So the גמרא
here is not distinguishing between חזיר chazir and dirt. It's saying you're
right, a normal שבועה shvua I won't eat would not include חזיר.
chazir. That's inedible. Okay, which is a funny idea. Okay, but the
end we're just saying that the guy explicitly said a שבועה shvua
he won't eat חזיר. chazir. So that does take effect the same
way you could say a שבועה shvua you won't eat dirt. So
the גמרא says, okay, one minute. So the גמרא says: מפרש נמי
גופא תיקשי. Meforesh nami gufa tikshei. Wait, wait, even if you were
explicit, it doesn't make sense. So fine, you said שבועה shvua you
won't eat חזיר, chazir, but still why does it take effect? אמאי
מושבע ועומד מהר סיני הוא? Amai mushba ve-omed me-har Sinai hu? This
is what we've seen before. You're already there's already a שבועה on
you not to eat that stuff from הר סיני. Har Sinai. All
right, so that means that this שבועה shouldn't take effect even if
you were explicit. So now we have the answer we've now said
third time we're saying this answer. רב ושמואל ורבי יוחנן Rav u'Shmuel
ve'Rabbi Yochanan דאמרי d'amri רב ושמואל ורבי יוחנן Rav u'Shmuel ve'Rabbi Yochanan
all say בכולל דבר המותר עם דבר האסור bekollel dvar hamutar im
dvar ha-asur that what you did is you said, a שבועה I
won't eat apples and חזיר. khazer. Okay, and in that case, because
the שבועה took effect on the apples, it also takes effect on
the חזיר. khazer. Okay? As long as the scope is bigger. We'll
discuss more of this tomorrow. וריש לקיש אמר אי אתה מוצא אלא
אם מפרש חצי שיעור ואליבא דרבנן. V'Reish Lakish amar ee ata motzei
ella im mefaresh chatzi shiur va'aliba d'rabbanan. No, if you just take
a bigger scope it won't take effect because still חזיר khazer you're
already forbidden in and it won't take effect on the חזיר. khazer.
The שבועה will only take effect if it forbids something that before
now you
were permitted to do. So what would be that case?
That you said a שבועה you won't eat a half of a
כזית kezayis of חזיר. khazer. That's something that it would take effect.
אי אתה מוצא Ee ata motzei you don't find it אלא אם
מפרש חצי שיעור ואליבא דרבנן. ella im mefaresh chatzi shiur va'aliba d'rabbanan.
Either you explicitly said, I won't eat a half of a כזית
kezayis of חזיר, khazer, according to the rabbis that you have to
be explicit, אי בסתם אליבא דרבי עקיבא, ee b'stam aliba d'Rabbi Akiva,
or according to remember Rabbi Akiva at the beginning, even if you
just said you won't eat, eat meaning by a שבועה even a
tiny amount. So for Reish Lakish, it's not enough that the scope
is bigger. If you want the שבועה to take effect on חזיר
khazer you have to forbid something that was permitted before now. And
that would only be a case if you forbade yourself to eat
less than a כזית. kezayis. Then it would take effect. דאמר, or
according to Rabbi Akiva you don't even have to be explicit, דאמר
אוסר עצמו בכל שהוא. D'amar oser et atzmo be'chol she'hu. Okay, because
he says a person makes himself forbidden even in a tiny amount.
So according to Rabbi Akiva, so that's how you why you forbid
something that was until now permitted. All right, so we will continue
with this tomorrow to see this debate about a שבועה that has
a bigger effect and a bigger scope and whether that sort of
solves this problem or not. All right, so until tomorrow.